Balaji Devaraj (1) Featured

Having 10 years of experience in IT industry implementing, developing and maintenance of various Web Based applications using Java, J2EE Technologies and Big Data Ecosystem such as Spark, Hive, Scala.



Current Designation: Lead Developer Total Experience: 10 Year(s) 0 Month(s)

Current Company: IQVIA Notice Period: 3 Months

Current Location: Bengaluru / Bangalore Highest Degree: B.Sc [Computers]

Functional Area: IT Software - Application Programming /

Maintenance

Role: Software Developer

Industry: IT-Software/Software Services

Pref. Location: Bengaluru / Bangalore

Marital Status: Single/unmarried

Key Skills: Big Data, Big Data Analytics, Scala, Spark, Hdfs, apache spark, Hive, Impala, Hadoop, SQL Server

Verified: Email - id Phone Number |

Last Active: 20-Jan-21 Last Modified: 20-Jan-21

Summary

I'm having totally about 9 years of experience and out of which first 6 years as Java/J2EE developer and last 3 years as Spark Scala developer. I have experience in building spark jobs to handle large datasets over 700GB. My primary skillsets are Apache Spark, Scala, Hive, Impala and other Hadoop ecosystem tools. I'm a blogger and also an active member on Stackoverflow.

Work Experience

IQVIA as Lead Developer Mar 2018 to Till Date

Design, Build, Test, Deploy solutions at scale. Interact with engineering team across geographies to leverage expertise and contribute to the project. Analysing business requirements and involving in development and coordinating with stack holders. Engage with project management and businesses teams to drive the agenda, set priorities and deliver high quality product features to keep the platform ahead of market scenarios. Identify right open source tools to deliver product features by performing research, POC or integrating with existing systems. develop/ contribute to add features that enable customer analytics at IQVIA scale. Deploy and implement best-in-class monitoring process to enable data applications meets SLAs

Verizon as Senior System Specialist Aug 2014 to Mar 2018

Responsible for requirement analysis, design, implementation and mentoring.

In charge of 4 modules out of 7 modules in the application.

Analyze new technologies and do POCs on them and give knowledge sessions to the teams.

Responsible for Junits of all the modules in the project and helping the team when challenges encountered. Received Spot Award for writing maximum Junits of my deliverables, motivating and encouraging the team to

adopt Junit as part of development life cycle.

Played an important role in DevOPs adaptation.

RavSoft Solutions Private Limited as Software Engineer

May 2013 to Jul 2014

Responsible for analysis, design, Implement server side components. Spearhead Requirement Gathering from the Client and spearhead

Responsible for Unit Testing, Peer Reviews and Design Reviews Contribution to Architectural Design

Lucid Technologies and Solutions Private Limited as Software Developer Dec 2010 to Apr 2013

Mentor a team of Junior developers in Development Architect Solutions from the scratch Maintaining Web services and Analyze Overall application Flow

Education

UG: B.Sc (Computers) from Annamalai University in 2010

Other Qualifications/Certifications/Programs:

GNIIT

IT Skills

Skill Name	Version Last Used Experience
Windows,Linux	
Apache Spark	
SCALA	2.10
Big Data	
SPARK	
SPARK	
HDFS	2.x
HIVE	

Languages Known

Language	Proficiency	Read	Write	Speak
English	Proficient			
Telugu	Proficient			
Tamil	Proficient			

Affirmative Action

Physically Challenged: No

Work Authorization

Job Type: Permanent

Employment Status: Full time